<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jescab01.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jescab01.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-24T13:12:09+00:00</updated><id>https://jescab01.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><entry><title type="html">JR’s bifurcation on C</title><link href="https://jescab01.github.io/blog/2025/bif_onC/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JR’s bifurcation on C"/><published>2025-02-24T12:32:41+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-24T12:32:41+00:00</updated><id>https://jescab01.github.io/blog/2025/bif_onC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jescab01.github.io/blog/2025/bif_onC/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="bifurcations-in-the-jansen-rit-model-over-parameter-c">Bifurcations in the Jansen-Rit Model Over Parameter C</h4> <p>Neural population models like the Jansen-Rit framework reveal complex dynamical transitions when tuning key parameters. In this post, I explore how varying C, the average number of synapses connecting subpopulations, leads to fundamental changes in the system’s fixed points and limit cycles.</p> <div> <iframe width="100%" height="600" src="/assets/html/PSE_overC.html" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> </div> <h4 id="the-role-of-synaptic-coupling-c-in-cortical-dynamics">The Role of Synaptic Coupling (C) in Cortical Dynamics</h4> <p>Parameter C controls the overall strength of synaptic interactions within a cortical column. As C increases, the model undergoes bifurcations that shift its behavior across different dynamical regimes.</p> <ul> <li>For low values of C, the system remains near a stable fixed point, with only minor noise-driven fluctuations in alpha-band activity.</li> <li>At intermediate C values (~135), the Jansen-Rit model exhibits a slow limit cycle, where oscillatory activity emerges but remains constrained.</li> <li>Near bifurcation points, we observe the transition from a pre-saddle node regime to a post-supercritical bifurcation, marking a qualitative shift in the system’s attractor landscape.</li> <li>For high C values, the limit cycle expands, producing robust oscillations characteristic of alpha rhythms.</li> </ul> <h4 id="fixed-points-limit-cycles-and-bifurcations">Fixed Points, Limit Cycles, and Bifurcations</h4> <p>The interactive figure below visualizes these transitions:</p> <ul> <li>Fixed points dominate for low C values.</li> <li>Limit cycles appear and expand around C ≈ 135, marking the transition from weak fluctuations to sustained oscillatory activity.</li> <li>As C increases further, the oscillatory regime stabilizes, reinforcing the role of synaptic coupling in shaping emergent neural dynamics.</li> </ul> <h4 id="takeaways-and-next-steps">Takeaways and Next Steps</h4> <p>This analysis highlights how intrinsic synaptic coupling (C) governs cortical excitability and transitions between quiescence and rhythmic activity. Future work could explore how parameter C interacts with external inputs or structural connectivity to refine predictions about cortical state transitions in health and disease.</p> <p>Let me know what you think—play with the interactive figure and share your insights!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="models"/><category term="jr"/><category term="nmm"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[how local synaptic coupling (C) modulates Jansen-Rit bifurcations]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jansen-Rit’s bifurcation</title><link href="https://jescab01.github.io/blog/2025/JR_bifurcation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jansen-Rit’s bifurcation"/><published>2025-02-24T11:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-24T11:40:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jescab01.github.io/blog/2025/JR_bifurcation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jescab01.github.io/blog/2025/JR_bifurcation/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="exploring-bifurcations-in-the-jansen-rit-model-with-an-interactive-brain-network-simulation">Exploring Bifurcations in the Jansen-Rit Model with an Interactive Brain Network Simulation</h4> <p>One of the fascinating aspects of brain network models (BNMs) is their ability to capture complex dynamical transitions observed in empirical brain activity. In the following plot, I explore how the Jansen-Rit model—originally designed to simulate cortical column activity—undergoes bifurcations when modulating the coupling factor that scales the weights of the structural connectivity matrix.</p> <div> <iframe width="100%" height="900" src="/assets/html/Criticality_th_noisy_phetero.html" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" scrolling="no" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> </div> <div class="caption"> The interactive figure illustrates the effect of the coupling factor (g) on brain network dynamics using the Jansen-Rit model. The slider at the top controls g, which is represented as a vertical line in the rPLV plot (top middle). As g increases, different brain regions (colored lines) transition through the bifurcation at varying levels due to heterogeneity in structural connectivity weights. This distribution across the bifurcation highlights how regions exhibit distinct dynamical shifts. The bottom row displays a segment of the simulated signals for each region, showing the evolution of oscillatory activity as a function of coupling strength. In these simulations, high noisy input to thalamus keeps the cortical nodes oscillating in the fixed point regimes. </div> <h4 id="the-role-of-coupling-in-large-scale-brain-dynamics">The Role of Coupling in Large-Scale Brain Dynamics</h4> <p>In BNMs, the <strong>coupling factor (g)</strong> determines the strength of interactions between brain regions, based on a connectivity matrix derived from diffusion MRI (here, using the AAL parcellation). As <strong>g</strong> increases, local neural populations transition from independent activity to collective dynamics, which can lead to dramatic shifts in oscillatory behavior.</p> <p>The interactive visualization above demonstrates this process:</p> <ul> <li>At <strong>low coupling values</strong>, signals generated by the model are operating in a fixed point regime.</li> <li>As <strong>g increases</strong>, long-range inputs alter both spectral properties and the temporal structure of the oscillations.</li> <li>Around <strong>critical points (bifurcations)</strong>, abrupt changes in signal amplitude and coherence occur, shifting the model’s behavior into a new dynamical regime: the limit cycle.</li> <li>These transitions also influence the <strong>functional connectivity (FC)</strong> patterns, where the correlation between empirical and simulated FC varies as a function of g.</li> </ul> <h4 id="key-takeaways">Key Takeaways</h4> <ul> <li>The Jansen-Rit model exhibits <strong>bifurcation points</strong> as a function of structural connectivity scaling.</li> <li>Modulating <strong>coupling strength (g)</strong> induces qualitative shifts in neural activity patterns.</li> <li>The correlation between empirical and simulated <strong>functional connectivity</strong> dynamically changes across these transitions.</li> </ul> <p>I’d love to hear your thoughts—feel free to interact with the plot and share any insights or questions! 🚀</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="models"/><category term="nmm"/><category term="jr"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[on coupling factor shaping brain dynamics and functional connectivity.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">welcome</title><link href="https://jescab01.github.io/blog/2025/welcome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="welcome"/><published>2025-02-24T10:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-24T10:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jescab01.github.io/blog/2025/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jescab01.github.io/blog/2025/welcome/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Welcome to My Digital Home</strong></p> <p>Hello and welcome! I’m thrilled you’ve stopped by to explore my personal space on the web—a place where I share not only my research projects but also the journey behind them.</p> <p>On this site, you’ll find an overview of my academic and professional pursuits. From detailed descriptions of my research projects and a comprehensive CV, to a curated list of publications and links to my code repositories, every section reflects my dedication to innovation and discovery. Whether you’re a fellow researcher, a prospective collaborator, or simply curious about what I do, there’s plenty here to spark your interest.</p> <p>Beyond the formal pages, this blog is where I let my thoughts roam free. I’ll be sharing insights about my work, updates on current projects, reflections on challenges and breakthroughs, and occasional musings about the ever-evolving landscape of technology and research. My goal is to create a space that’s not only informative but also engaging—a place where ideas can be exchanged and inspiration can flourish.</p> <p>Thank you for visiting. I invite you to explore the various sections of my site, and I look forward to connecting with you, whether through a comment on a blog post or a direct message. Here’s to the beginning of many insightful conversations and shared discoveries!</p> <p>Cheers, J.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a warm introduction to my digital portfolio]]></summary></entry></feed>